{
  "reference_number": "1828",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Look at the wide variety of options that are simple, small, cost effective. Things like electric bikes, and buses, reducing wasteful\n packaging on all products, working from home initiatives. Encouraging work from home - even one day a week would reduce traffic\n\n emissions buy 20% overnight. Other initiatives like this would be much more useful."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Targets can be set after government changes its attitude to offering 'carrots' to reduce emissions rather than taxing those who can\n least afford it and putting into place initiatives that will impact most on the working poor."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Strongly opposed to international carbon units."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, absolutely. No-one can read the future, we can just make guesses of what might happen. Looking back at guesses made in the\n past, I can think of several that were completely wrong and none that were right. So this will just be a guess."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It depends on what level the emissions budgets will be set. There is always a 'carrot and stick' in these sorts of things and 'carrots'\n work much better than 'sticks'."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "with the best will in the world, it is all guess work and of course a government must be allowed to adjust according to the situation as\n it unfolds."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "yes, for the same reasons laid out in qu 6."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Huge consideration must be given to those most affected in their daily lives by the decisions being made - the little man, the\neveryday people who are working to make ends meet. It's also exceedingly important that large corporations are not given leeway\n\nand allowed benefits because of lobbying and pressure from them."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Advisory only."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Advisory only with absolutely no power. The CCC is not elected by the people, the government is."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Would like to see included those who are aware of the long term effects of environmental damage on weather, rather than focusing\nonly on emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "sounds like another gravy train"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am seriously concerned about the environmental damage being caused by things like deforestation and intensive farming. Things\nlike deforestation are actually causing weather pattern changes which are impacting us more than emissions. Also, we need to keep\na calm approach to things - extreme weather events are part of the history of our planet and not necessarily caused by emissions."
    }
  ]
}
